Guide to the Sir William Jones Manuscripts MSS.301
Fales Library and Special Collections
Sir William Jones Manuscripts
circa 1100-1794
Fales Library and Special Collections
Jones, William, Sir, 1746-1794
MSS.301
2.5 Linear Feet in 3 flat boxes
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Biographical Note
William Jones (1746-1794) was a British lawyer in India and pioneer of comparative linguistic studies. Born in London in 1746, Jones later enrolled at University College, Oxford in 1764 and began studying linguistics and Oriental culture and literature. Jones studied Greek, Latin, Persian, Arabic and Sanskrit, becoming an expert in the field of comparative and historic linguistics. He spent several years after graduating working on translations of texts from these languages. After receiving his degree, he studied law at Middle Temple in London from 1770-1773. In 1772, William Jones became a fellow of the Royal Society as well as a practicing lawyer.
In 1783 he was knighted, becoming Sir William Jones, and was appointed to a position as a judge in British-controlled India. Jones continuted his studies of Oriental languages and literature in India, and during this time produced additional translations as well as original works. In addition to language and literature, Jones produced works on botony, astrology, zoology and law. In 1784 Sir William Jones founded the Asiatic Society with the purpose of promoting the study of Asiatic cultures and languages. Jones continued his studies and his work as a judge until his death in Calcutta in 1794.
Sources: Cannon, Garland. The Collected Works of Sir William Jones, Vol., New York: NYU Press, 2003.
Jones, Sir William.The Poetical Works of Sir William Jones with the life of the author, Vol.1 London: Cadell and Davies, 1807.
Provenance
Fales purchased the materials from Jones scholar Garland Cannon with a generous donation from artist, writer and philanthropist Kevin Brine, an active supporter of the Elmer Holmes Bobst Library.
Scope and Contents
The Sir William Jones Manuscripts consist of various types of documents related to his lingustic studies, many in their original language with translations or notation by Jones. Included are documents in Sanskrit and Persian relating to astrology, botany and law.
Manuscripts, Bengali.; Marginalia (annotations); Manuscripts, Sanskrit.; Devanagari type.; zodiac.; Linguistics.; India -- History -- British occupation, 1765-1947.; Oriental philology.; Manuscripts, Persian.; Jones, William, Sir, 1746-1794
- Series I: Manuscripts
  - Legal Mutation, undated; cuid36302 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Sanskrit written in Bengali characters. Refers to rules and regulations for donations/inheritance. Written in formal hand by a Brahmin scholar or pundit.
  - Numbered sentences/slokas from 9-14, undated; cuid36304 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Sanskrit in Bengali characters. Jones' handwriting with spelling corrections. Page number 3
  - Numbered sentences/slokas from 1-3, undated; cuid36305 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Sanskrit in Bengali characters. Page number 1
  - Planet/zodiac related words, undated; cuid36306 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. Jones' handwriting
  - Short note, undated; cuid36307 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Sanskrit in Bengali characters.
  - unidentified document, undated; cuid36308 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Extract in Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. Formal hand. English annotation by Jones. Mention of Jaitra Singh the ruler of Mewar (AD 1200)
  - Letter/short note to a senior person, undated; cuid36309 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters.
  - Short note, undated; cuid36310 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Sanskrit in Bengali characters. Handmade paper rust/brown colored – writing in black ink
  - 2 lines of slokas/note, undated; cuid36311 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Sanskrit in Bengali characters
  - Slokas about the 'chatak' birds' love for the pure rain water and clouds, undated; cuid36312 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - unidentified document, undated; cuid36317 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters, written in formal hand by a pundit.Handmade paper with writing in black ink and punctuation marks in red ink
  - unidentified document, undated; cuid36318 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. Formal writing by pundit – also Jones' handwriting. Back of page – English – reference to Varaha Mihira – an Indian astronomer, astrologer and mathematician. Also mention of Bhattotpala – the commentator of Brihat Jataka
  - Numbered slokas, undated; cuid36313 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Sanskrit in Bengali characters. Last 2 lines are Sanskrit in Devanagari characters.
  - Numbered slokas, undated; cuid36314 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - unidentified document, undated; cuid36315 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. 4 page hand stitched notebook. First three pages are printed. The last page is Jones' handwriting – annotations for spellings and pronunciations of various Sanskrit words
  - Translations of the Gayatri Mantra (prayer), undated; cuid36356 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Sanskrit mantra written in English characters.
  - unidentified document, undated; cuid36334 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. Back of page – notes and calculations in Jones' handwriting.
  - unidentified document, undated; cuid36335 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. 2 sentences in Persian
  - Scansions of poetry using Indian musical notations/symbols, undated; cuid36355 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    The other side of notebook has list of names in pencil – British officers and friends perhaps.
  - unidentified document, undated; cuid36342 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Persian, 2 pages. I page Persian in English characters. Last page Persian in Jones' handwriting. Hand stitched notebook – writing in black ink.
  - Preface to the Varahas Almanac for 1789, cuid36322 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. Annotated in English - Jones' handwriting. Includes zodiac calculations
  - Manuscript on Vetalapancavinsati by Sivadasa, undated; cuid36329 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. 29 verses written in several hands – black ink. Hand painted notebook cover.
  - unidentified document, undated; cuid36359 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters
  - unidentified document, undated; cuid36360 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Sanskrit in Bengali characters written by Nimai Pandit. Single sentence on the top is in Jones' handwriting.
  - 'Yoga Vasistha.', undated; cuid36336 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. Annotated in English - Jones' handwriting. It is the discourse between Sage Vasistha and Lord Rama regarding truth and spiritual liberation.
  - Short Note, undated; cuid36337 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. Back of page reads "A Letter."
  - Floor plan, undated; cuid36338 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Diagrams in red ink. Sanskrit in Devanagari characters – in black ink. Both sides of small note paper.
  - "Amara Cosha.", undated; cuid36339 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Sanskrit in Bengali characters. Title in English in Jones' handwriting. It is the oldest known dictionary in the world – classical Sanskrit vocabulary written by Sage Amara Sinha.
  - Notes on the Gayatri Mantra, undated; cuid36345 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Sanskrit in Bengali characters. Annotated by Jones. Writing in red ink, hand stitched 5 note books.
  - Letter from Garland Cannon, 2003; cuid36348 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    William Jones Accretions, 2003.
  - unidentified document, undated; cuid36349 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Single document in Arabic/Persian. Single document in Arabic/Persian (?)
  - Legalities of Inheritance/Donation, undated; cuid36350 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Single document in Bengali
  - Chart of Indian Zodiac signs (Raashi) in Devanagari characters, undated; cuid36301 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Annotations in English & Persian. Original of the one printed later in Jones' "On the Antiquity of the Indian Zodiac." Annotation include seasons, planets & days of the week.
  - Manuscript on Ramadeva's poem Vivduanmodatarangini (Fountain of pleasure to the learned.), undated; cuid36325 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Sanskrit in Bengali characters. Black in on brown paper. Inscription on cover is in English – "The Bidwan Mod Tarungeenee from the Gooptu Para Pundit of Santipore."
  - "The Opening of the Shahnamah in the characters of the Zend.", undated; cuid36343 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Title in English. Rest of the manuscript in Persian. Shahnamah (The Book of Kings was written by Iranian poet Ferdowsi in 1000AD).
  - unidentified document, undated; cuid36353 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Two Persian words on cover - translated by Garland Cannon as BAZI SAT meaning "game" "chess". Material inside is foliated and perhaps does not relate/belong to the cover. Content inside written in Sanskrit in Bengali characters. Reference to Krishna and Arjun.
  - "The Hindu Ecliptick.", undated; cuid36331 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
    English. Diagram of globe with zodiac and seasons.
  - "A Hymn to the Night from the Veda.", undated; cuid36324 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Single sheet. English. Jones' handwriting
  - "The Hindu Ecliptick.", undated; cuid36333 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Translation of Necker used in 'On the mystical Poetry of the Persians and Hindus.', undated; cuid36327 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    English - Jones' handwriting.
  - "Account of the Method of Van Reede. Mr. W. Jones' Ms.", undated; cuid36328 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Opening translation from Reede tot Drakenstein's (1673) close to verbatim 'Botanical Observations on Select Indian Plants.'
  - "Indian Grant of Law to the Priests of Siva.", undated; cuid36357 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Devanagari and English characters. Last Page – "Reverence to Ganesha."
  - "Translation of the poetry at Vindya Mountains.", undated; cuid36361 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. Annotated by Jones.
  - "Stanzas in praise of the Ganga.", undated; cuid36362 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. Written in black ink. Persian words in red ink. Annotated in English by Jones. "King Akbar's minister Bairam Khan – a Muslim – but a poet in Sanskrit wrote several stanzas in praise of the Ganga." (river).
  - Extracts from the Vedas, undated; cuid36367 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Commencing with "May that soul of mine…" English - Jones' handwriting
  - Writings/Translations from the Yajurveda, undated; cuid36365 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    English - Jones' handwriting. (Man as a tree).
  - "Astronomical terms in Sanskrit used in Mr. Davis' paper, undated; cuid36326 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. Annotated in English - Jones' handwriting
  - Letter to William Jones about Amin Sahab Manuscript, 1786-09-30; cuid36358 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Persian. Handmade paper with watermark.
    According to the work of Umrat Khan, Graduate Student Assistant in Special Collections, and her Persian tutor, Hijaz Mehdi, this letter, addressed to Sir William Jones, is from an unknown author about a manuscript by Mr. Amin Sahab. The letter is written in sangi chaap, a spiral form of writing, and in Shekesteh Nastaliq or broken script.
    The majority of the letter focuses on the unknown author's praises of Sir William Jones and his wife. The author also mentions a manuscript received from Mr. Amin Sahab.
    English Translation
    Page 1 Standing in tribute in the court of hazūr (Sir) who is a treasure of grace, and has Aristotle's intellect. Who is in a position of decree, with highness in degree and rank, grandeur stature, and is the most virtuous of people. The fountain from where wisdom and knowledge springs, whose flag is high, respectable of the gods, I mean, Sir William Younus (Jones),may his great shade prolong.
    It is delivered, God willing. May the God of all the worlds, keep the age and wealth of that king green and fresh for 150 years. And I am and I have been busy continuously praying and praising for Sir's blessed self. I hope my prayer reaches the target like an arrow, by the Grace of the God of servants.
    After expressing my sincerity, my disclosed opinion may not remain hidden from the bright self of that Sir (William Jones). May you have the best of times, and the most blessed moments. With that letter, from the praiseful pen, Sir (William Jones) honored this man (the author of the letter) in that sun-like document containing well-doings of the praised personality of that Sir (William Jones). And the good news of wellness of the carrier of innocence and immaculacy, offspring of the royals,famous in all the land and sea, Mary of the times, Miss Lady Jones, may God prolong her good luck.
    Hope you receive this letter in times of happiness and moments of luck. I hope your time will be with ease and without burden.
    Words of the text that Mr Amin delivered to me, the sirafraz namcha (chapter), was a manuscript in Pahlavi language and handwritten. He has put all his effort and says this is a chapter, however I remember very little of it. God willing, as per your wish, I will write back to you in detail, when my senses are working better, so you can see it as well.
    I am so excited to meet you (I am passionate about kissing your feet), that to describe it with pen in a letter is impossible. I wanted to write a letter earlier but there is an ancient tradition amongst Persian people that when an individual leaves for a destination, his family will not write to him until they receive a letter from him first.
    As your letter has reached now I am encouraged to write back and express in your presence with hopeful request that you will honor this humble well-wisher with two blessed words of mercy (for me).
    This will be the reason for you to pray and a reason for my heart's contentment. This will be the most minimal outcome. And may your wealth/riches last forever.
    The letter is written on the date of 30th September 1786 AD, at the port of Calcutta at the house of Mr Amin Sahab. May my offer of sincerity be delivered in the presence of Her Highness who is at the Queen's stature, the Mary of the times, the one and only lady Jones Sahiba (Miss), may she stay well forever Inshaa Allah (God-willing), may your orders remain obeyed.
    Page 2 (unrecognized text)
    (Persian) (Yours sincerely) (Bahman [Iranian month])
    Other Finding Aids
    NYU Special Collections has a Persian transcription of this document, as well as an image demonstrating the order in which the script should be read, available for researchers upon request.
  - "The Ignorant Instructed.", undated; cuid36364 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Sixteen stanzas of Moha Mudgara by Adi Sankaracharya. A short poem about the transitory nature of worldly experience – everlasting bliss can be gained through knowledge – the higher light. Original translations from Sanskrit to English.
  - Extracts from the Vedas, Mahabharata and Shastras, undated; cuid36363 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. Annotated in English. Handmade paper, watermarked.
  - Jones' translations of extracts from the Vedas, undated; cuid36368 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    English
  - Translations from the Vedas – "What Relish Can There Be…", undated; cuid36366 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - List of Sanskrit words and stanzas, undated; cuid36352 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Annotations by Jones. Some words are names of deities and characters from the Ramayana and Mahabharata. General study of word meaning and spelling. Also includes a study of chhand (poetic meter). The Vedas contain Varnik and Matrik chhands.
  - "Isavasyam" or And Upanishad from the Yajurveda, undated; cuid36340 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    English translation of the Sanskrit text.
  - Plans of Knowledge, undated; cuid36320 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    English. Jones' handwriting. 2 lines in Sanskrit. The cover reads "Paper of Literary Projects."
  - Sanskrit slokas (verses), undated; cuid36303 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Written in Bengali characters. Formal writing. Handmade paper – rust/brown colored – writing in black ink.
  - "Genera of plants growing between Arifnagar and Khidirpur.", 1794; cuid36330 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    English - Jones' handwriting. Incomplete, unpublished part of his catalog of Indian plants growing in Calcutta (1794).
  - Nala and Damayanti, undated; cuid36347 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Hindu mythological narrative. Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. Annotated by Jones.
  - Draft of Jones' translation of Gita Govinda – verses 4,5 & 6, c. 1790; cuid36351 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    (circa 1790). Originally composed by a Sanskrit poet Jayadeva. First English translation by Jones published in 1792. Othersie of page has Vedic slokas in Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. Annotated in Jones'writing.
  - "On the Primitive Religion of the Hindus.", undated; cuid36344 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    English – Jones' handwriting.
  - "A Hindu Almanac for the year of Saca – Beginning Sat 11th April 1789 by a Pandit of Navadwip, surnamed Vidya Siromani.", cuid36323 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. English annotations in Jones' handwriting. Mention of important festivals and auspicious occasions. Hand stitched notebook – handmade paper with silk cover
  - Names of ancient Hindu texts and also newer (navin) ones, undated; cuid36316 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. Annotated by Jones. Dated 20th July and 17th Aug 1788. Place – Benaras
  - "Address to the Goddess Saraswati.", undated; cuid36341 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Title on cover page. English. 13 verses translated from Sanskrit. Jones' handwriting.
  - "Varahas Almanac", 1789; cuid36321 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    A calendar – 1789 – twelve months beginning from April. Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. Also astrological study of lunar cycles
  - Translation of Omar Khayyam's Rubaiyat (Quatrains), undated; cuid36319 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Persian and English. Handwritten by Jones.
  - Chart of Hindi verbs, undated; cuid36369 (Box Shared Fales 073, Folder 12)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters with detailed explanations in English. Handmade paper. Writing in black ink.
  - "Bengali Translation of the Dandakaumudi" (Punishment for Crime), undated; cuid36346 (Box Shared Fales 073, Folder 13)
    Codes of judicial procedures.
  - Formal declaration about various Shastras (disciplines of knowledge.), undated; cuid36354 (Box Shared Fales 073, Folder 14)
    Document in Sanskrit in Bengali characters.
  - "The Yoga Stars.", undated; cuid36332 (Box Shared Fales 073, Folder 15)
    English. A chart with names of stars (nakshatras) along with the longitudes and latitudes.